Well, welcome back from the break. Let's
talk wash now because you know Ghana's
progress in water uh sanitation and
hygiene is anchored in national policies
aligned with sustainable development
goals with government intervention
spanning rural water expansion urban
sanitation infrastructure hygiene
campaigns and public private
partnerships.
However, we enforcement maintenance gaps
and uneven access especially in Royal
and Perry urban areas continue to limit
impact. So how do we deal with all of
that? Today I've been joined by two
people who are involved in in this area
to help us understand what needs to
change, what needs to happen for us to
achieve the sustainable development
goals in terms of wash. And I'm joined
in studio uh by Joseph Matthew. I mean
if you hear the name, we should tell you
where he's coming from, right? Uh he's
Wash project lead and communications
coordinator of United Way Ghana. Joseph,
good morning.
>> Tr you good?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. I'm well. Uh okay.
>> Thanks for having us. Ah, thanks for
coming. So, you are a you are a a a
worry boy or a Lagos boy?
>> I'm a Lagos boy.
>> Lagos, huh? Okay. All right. And Gifty
Osu, a sustainability advocate with
Credential Life Insurance Ghana.
>> Oh, okay. All right, then. How are you
doing, Gifty?
>> I'm well. Yes,
>> I'm I'm well. Uh Joseph, let me start
with you. Now when we talk about
investment
>> uh you know in infrastructure to promote
uh wash especially in rural and perry
urban areas where is Ghana and uh is
government doing enough?
>> Um thank you for the question. Um I
believe um currently Ghana has um Ghana
is doing significantly well when it
comes to water sanitation and hygiene
especially water access. So according to
a joint uh monitoring program by the WHO
and UNICEF about 78%
to um 90% of Ghanaians are covered when
it comes to access to water.
>> You understand? And at the same time um
the only
>> about how many%
>> about um 87 to 90%
>> covered
>> covered when it comes to access to
water.
>> Okay.
>> Yes. But the challenge that we've seen
based on the data is sanitation. So
sanitation is usually a big challenge
and currently about 15% of Ghanaians are
have proper and safe sanitation. So you
keep 15%. So you know that is um that is
something we need to look at and that's
where you know as an organization as an
NGO we are trying to bridge the gap and
ensure that we promote access to proper
and safe sanitation within per urban and
local communities um in Ghana. You know
there is a lot of um sea side
communities of which Choco is one for
example and you find that a lot of those
communities usually suffer from flooding
and other um climate um challenges. So
mostly we tend to want to bridge the gap
by ensuring that we work with government
agencies, we work with donor partners to
provide those um those sanitation needs
that these communities um are requiring
and you know provide also other
instruments and infrastructure that
would help reduce the the this the
relatively poor state of sanitation.
this the the the percentage of access to
water does it capture those in the galia
affected areas too
>> or do we have a distin distinction
between clean and just water
>> yes that's a good question yes I think
it's it's it's generally access to water
not necessarily whether the water is
clean or not it's a general access to
water you know that at the same time we
already know the existing challenges
that the water corporations might have
across board of which like you mentioned
Ghana say is one of them but that is
outside the scope of our work
>> but whichever the case having access to
water it's something I think Ghana
relatively is doing well at but we need
to improve more on sanitation
>> how does our strategy compare with other
African countries and
where and how do we bridge the gap
>> yes so relatively Ghana is doing well
like I said um Ghana has no deficiency
or shortfall when it comes to proper
policies I think where we need to bridge
the gap on is implementation of those
policies. You understand? Where we need
to um deise a scheme and a process where
government can bring more corporate and
donor partners on board so that these
donor partners buy into the existing
policies and help bridge the financing
gap. Because what we've really come to
understand is government can't do it all
by themsel. They need donor partnership.
They need private sector partnership to
also buy into the scheme and help
achieve the um access to water,
sanitation and hygiene goals. So um
bridging that financial gap is where the
donor partners and NOS's are trying to
fill in and we're working with various
government agencies right from so we are
doing a bottom top approach. So we are
working from the municipals to the you
know regional and then to the national
system where we can buy into the
government policies.
>> Let me bring in gifting now gift. So I
guess the pro is credential something.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So as Joseph rightly mentioned um
wash is one of the topical issues that
ought to be addressed and for us at
credential life insurance Ghana we are
working closely with United Way Ghana to
implement what we call the proclimate
action and this is a 100,000 USD project
in Choco being funded by the prudence
foundation and so what this project
seeks to do is to improve sanitation and
wash within the community and we have
actually seen
sterling impacts or performance over the
period being we started sometime last
year. So is to construct 100
biodigesttor toilet facilities for homes
which we are nearing nearing completion
and then also we have constructed 20
seater toilet facility for the chimana
cluster of school. This this is a school
that has about 450 students and in terms
of toilet facility we say that it was
not functioning so we had to quickly
come in. So you have people coming to
school they do not have toilet facility
whenever they want to visit nature
school they have to ask for permission
to go and some of them go out and look
for toilet facility and some of them
turn out not coming back to school again
which was really impacting performance
and then also in terms of turnout for
student and so this intervention was
quickly to come in to really ensure that
this challenge is being solved and
beyond that one of the key As Joseph
mentioned,
we know impact of climate change. We
talk about it. It exacerbating the whole
wash or less the water and sanitation
problem. And I you clearly stated Galam,
right? Which is one of the serious major
issues. Okay. And one of the things that
we realized that we could do is
co-creating because if you don't think
with the people and have them at the
center of what you are doing then at the
end of at the end of the day ownership
is something that will be left out
because at the end of it all you are
doing something for the society you're
doing something for the community. So if
the community people are not part of the
conversation, do not have clear
ownership and know their role that they
have to play then it's going to be a
very problematic. So what we tend to do
was to really ensure that we have the
grassroot people being part of this. So
I believe that from the global
perspective or even from the national
perspective what we can do is that
whenever we are doing such interventions
the very core people or the recipients
of these interventions ought to be part
of the conversation and once we do that
we are able to ensure that if the donor
or the NGO is done with their job and
they are no more in the community you
have people to really take care of these
interventions And and I guess that
should also come in with a government
plan. Yes.
>> So NOS's like yourselves doing it must
it be isolated or it must be tied into
the national strategic plan.
>> It must be tied into the national
strategic plan. And one of the things
that is it's a gap not not just for our
part of the world but I'll say Africa in
general is that you realize that some
way somehow some of these NOS's they
don't work they work in silos which
shouldn't be the case when you are
working you need to work closely with
the government ensure that whatever you
are doing ties into the strategy of the
government what the government has and
you need to ensure that you have the
core stakeholders involved in the
conversation and I'm very happy that
What we do with United Way, we have the
assemblies being part of it. We ensure
that the core elements or stakeholders
that ought to be involved in the
conversation are really part of it. And
this is what we need to do because you
can't work in silos. Okay? When you're
doing an intervention and let's say from
the macro level, you don't have the
government oversight. Government is not
even aware of what you are doing. you
are doing something that is not in
alignment with what government expect
then is going to be a very a big
challenge. So we really have to ensure
that there's that kind of thing with
government intervent.
>> All right Joseph just before we wrap up
what will be your concluding remarks uh
touching on what government should do uh
to better the relationship between NGO
and government in ensuring that our war
strategies are achieved.
>> Yes please. I think um government needs
to have an open policy when it comes to
partnering with NOS's and other private
sector donor partners. We need to see
the fact that it is not a one-man
business. It's not a one institution
business. You see with our project we
are welcoming co-creating like she said
and collaborations not just with one
donor partner with multiple donors and
adopting communities for multi-year
projects. You understand? So that it's
not just you go into a community for one
year and you go out. You have multiple
years of working with the communities
and having multiple donor partners work
with them providing different um needs
that the community needs in terms of
access to water, sanitation and hygiene
and I think government should buy into
the same um framework where you know we
all work in collaborations because as
she has mentioned government lays the
policy they understand the design and
the architectural plan for these
communities. So we are simply buying
into that existing policy and we can't
do it without them. On our project we
work hand in hand with the Acra
Metropolitan and Assembly specifically
the Abloma South submetro and we
>> the major stakeholder in the project and
we are doing well to make sure that we
flow along with what they have planned
out.
>> All right. Okay.
Just 30 seconds. You have any concluding
remarks?
>> Yes. So what I'll say is that um one
organization cannot do it all. It's very
important that we have other
stakeholders, other pirate entities,
NOS's coming on board and with the fact
that now we have some limited funding,
we need to own it as a country and see
how best we can come together to solve
this challenge. Yeah, thank you.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Thank you very Um, Joseph Matthew is
wash project lead and communications
coordinator United Way Ghana and gifts
who is sustainability advocate with uh,
Credential Life Insurance Ghana.
>> Yes,
>> I got it right.
>> Yes, you got it right. Thank you.
>> That's what it is. Well, we'll end it
here.